Have you ever been asked by your Chinese friend,
هل سألك صديقك الصيني يوماً.
"What is your zodiac sign?"
"ماهو برجك الصيني؟"
Don't think they are making small talk.
الا تعتقد انها ملائمة للمحادثات القصيرة.
If you say, "I'm a Monkey,"
فإن أجبت انك من برج "القرد"،
they immediately know
فسيعلمون تلقائياً
you are either 24, 36, 48 or 60 years old.
اإن عمرك هو إما 24، 36، 48 او 60 عام.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Asking a zodiac sign is a polite way of asking your age.
السؤال عن برجك هو أذاً طريقة مهذبة لمعرفة عمرك.
By revealing your zodiac sign, you are also being evaluated.
وبكشف برجك ، يتم كذلك تقييمك.
Judgments are being made about your fortune or misfortune,
ويتم الحكم علي كونك محظوظا او غير محظوظ،
your personality, career prospects
وعلي شخصيتك ، ومستقبلك الوظيفي
and how you will do in a given year.
وكيف ستكون في سنة معينة.
If you share you and your partner's animal signs,
ولو اخبرت الاخرين عن برجك وبرج شريكك،
they will paint a picture in their mind about your private life.
فسوف يرسمون صورة في خيالهم عن حياتك الخاصة.
Maybe you don't believe in the Chinese zodiac.
ربما انت لا تعتقد في الابراج الصينية.
As a quarter of the world population is influenced by it,
وحيث ان ربع سكان العالم متاثرين بها،
you'd be wise to do something about that.
سيكون من الافضل ان تفعل شيئا حيال ذلك.
So what is the Chinese zodiac, exactly?
حسناً ماهي الابراج الصينية ، بالضبط؟
Most Westerners think of Greco-Roman zodiac,
معظم الغربيين يظنونها الابراج الاغريقية-الرومانية،
the signs divided into 12 months.
تلك الرموز المقسمة على ١٢ شهراًَ.
The Chinese zodiac is different.
الابراج الصينية شيء مختلف.
It's a 12-year cycle labeled with animals,
انها عبارة عن دورة من ١٢ سنة، مسماة باسماء حيوانات
starting with a Rat and ending with a Pig,
تبداء بالفأر وتنتهي بالخنزير.
and has no association with constellations.
وليس لها ارتباط بالمجموعات النجمية.
For example, if you were born in 1975, you are a Rabbit.
مثلا اذا كنت مولود عام 1975 فـأنت أرنب.
Can you see your zodiac sign there?
هل تستطيع أن ترى برجك هنا؟
Our Chinese ancestors constructed a very complicated theoretical framework
لقد كون اسلافنا الصينين إطار نظري معقد
based on yin and yang, the five elements and the 12 zodiac animals.
مرتكزاً على اليانغ ، والعناصرالخمسة وابراج الحيوانات الاثني عشر.
Over thousands of years,
ولإلأف السنين،
this popular culture has affected people's major decisions,
هذه الثقافة الشائعة اثرت على قرارات الناس الكبيرة،
such as naming, marriage, giving birth and attitude towards each other.
مثل تسمية الابناء، الزواج، الولادة، والسلوك مع الاخرين.
And some of the implications are quite amazing.
وبعض التاثيرات الاخرى محيرة حقاً.
The Chinese believe certain animals get on better than the others.
يعتقد الصينيون ان بعض الحيوانات تحقق نجاحا افضل من الاخريات.
So parents choose specific years to give birth to babies,
لذلك يختار الوالدين سنة بعينها لإنجاب الاطفال.
because they believe the team effort by the right combination of animals
لأنهم يعتقدون ان العمل الجماعي والجمع الموفق بين الابراج
can give prosperity to families.
ستمنح العائلات التقدم والازدهار.
We even refer to the zodiac when entering into romantic relations.
حتى اننا نستشير الابراج عند الدخول في العلاقة العاطفية.
I'm a Pig; I should have perfect romance with Tigers, Goats and Rabbits.
انا برج الخنزير، شريكي الافضل يكون اما النمر، المعزة أوالارنب.
Chinese people believe some animals are natural enemies.
يعتقد الصينيون أن بعض الحيوانات تشكل اعداء طبيعيين.
As a Pig, I need to be careful with a Snake.
انا كخنزير على ان احترس من الثعبان،
Raise your hand if you are a Snake.
ارفعوا ايديكم ايها الثعابين.
Let's have a chat later.
سيكون لنا حديث لاحقاً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We believe some animals are luckier than the others,
نعتقد ان بعض الأبراج محظوظة اكثر من غيرها،
such as the Dragon.
مثل التنين.
Unlike the Western tradition,
خلافا للتقاليد الغربية،
the Chinese Dragon is a symbol for power, strength and wealth.
فإن التنين الصيني يرمز للسلطة، والقوة، والثروة.
It's everyone's dream to have a Dragon baby.
حلم كل شخص ان يحصل على طفل تنين.
Jack Ma's parents must have been very proud.
لابد من ان والدا "جاك ما" كانو فخورين جدا.
And they are not the only ones.
وليسو هم الوحيدين.
In 2012, the Year of the Dragon,
في عام 2012، عام التنين،
the birthrate in China, Hong Kong and Taiwan
عدد المواليد في الصين، هونكوك وتايوان
increased by five percent.
ازداد بمقدار خمسة في المئة.
That means another one million more babies.
هذا يعني مليون طفل جديد.
With a traditional preference to baby boys,
وبما ان التقاليد تفضل المواليد الذكور،
the boy-girl ratio that year was 120 to 100.
كانت نسبة الذكور للإناث ذلك العام 120-100.
When those Dragon boys grow up,
وعندما يكبر اطفال التنين هؤلاء،
they will face much more severe competition in love and job markets.
فسيواجهون منافسة مستعره في مجال الحب والعمل.
According to the BBC and the Chinese government's press release,
بحسب تصريحات بي بي سي والحكومة الصينية،
January 2015 saw a peak of Cesarean sections.
فإن يناير 2015 شهد اعلى معدل للعمليات القيصرية.
Why?
لماذا؟
That was the last month for the Year of the Horse.
لأنه الشهر الاخير من عام الحصان.
It's not because they like horses so much,
ليس لانهم يحبون الحصان جداً،
it's because they try to avoid having unlucky Goat babies.
ولكن تفاديا لعام العنزة قليلة الحظ،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If you are a Goat, please don't feel bad.
لو كنت من برج المعنزة رجاءً لاتبتئس.
Those are Goat babies.
فهؤلاء أيضأ من برج العنزة.
They don't look like losers to me.
لا يبدون فاشلون بالنسبة لي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Tiger is another undesirable animal,
النمر أيضأ من الحيوانات الغير محبذة.
due to its volatile temperament.
بسبب مزاجة المتقلب.
Many Chinese regions saw a sharp decline of birthrate
شهدت الكثير من المقاطعات الصينية تناقصا في معدل المواليد
during those years.
في هذه السنوات.
Perhaps one should consider zodiac in reverse,
ربما يمكن ان نفكر في الابراج بطريقة عكسية،
as those Tiger and Goat babies will face much less competition.
إذ سيشهد مواليد النمر والعنزة منافسة اقل.
Maybe they are the lucky ones.
ربما هم المحظوظين فعلياً
I went through the Forbes top 300 richest people in the world,
لقد مررت على قائمة فوربس لأغني 300 شخص في العالم،
and it's interesting to see
من المثيرة للاهتمام ان نرى
the most undesirable two animals, the Goat and Tiger,
ان اكثر حيوانين غير مرغوبين، هما النمر والعنزة،
are at the top of the chart,
كانا في رأس القائمة،
even higher than the Dragon.
حتى اعلى من التنين.
So maybe we should consider,
ربما من الجدير اخذ ذلك في الاعتبار،
maybe it's much better to have less competition.
ربما من الجيد ان تواجه منافسة اقل.
One last but interesting point:
نقطة مهمة اخيرة:
many Chinese people make their investment decisions
العديد من الصينين يبنون قراراتهم المالية
based on the zodiac sign index.
استنادا على توقعات الابراج .
Although the belief and tradition of the zodiac sign
بالرغم من ان التقاليد والابراج
has been over thousands of years,
وجدت منذ الاف السنين،
the trend of using it in making major decisions
الا ان النزعة لاستخدامها في تقرير الامور المصيرية
did not really happen until the past few decades.
لم يحدث الا في العقود الاخيرة
Our ancestors were very busy surviving poverty, drought,
كان اسلافنا مشغولين بصراع البقاء ضد الفقر، والجفاف،
famine, riot, disease and civil war.
المجاعات، العنف، الامراض والحرب الاهلية.
And finally, Chinese people have the time, wealth and technology
واخيراً، وجد الصينيون الوقت، الثروة والتكنولوجيا
to create an ideal life they've always wanted.
لخلق حياة مثالية لطالما حلموا بها
The collective decision made by 1.3 billion people
قراراً جماعياً قرره 1.3 بليون شخص
has caused the fluctuation in economics and demand on everything,
تسببت في التقلبات الاقتصادية والطلب على كل شيء،
from health care and education to property and consumer goods.
من الرعاية الصحية والتعليم الى الاصول و السلع الاستهلاكية.
As China plays such an important role in the global economy and geopolitics,
وبما أن الصين تلعب دورا هاما في الاقتصاد والجغرافيا السياسية العالمية،
the decisions made based on the zodiac and other Chinese traditions
أن القرارات التي تقوم على الأبراج والتقاليد الصينية الأخرى
end up impacting everyone around the world.
في نهاية المطاف تؤثر على كل شخص في العالم.
Are there any Monkeys here?
هل هناك شخص من برج القرد هنا.
2016 is the Year of the Monkey.
2016 هو عام القرد.
Monkeys are clever, curious, creative and mischievous.
القرود ذكية، غريبة، مبدعة ومؤذية.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)